A Finding Aid to the Alma de Bretteville Spreckels Papers, 1920-1978, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Alma de Bretteville Spreckels papers
1920-1978
Archives of American Art
Spreckels, Alma de Bretteville, 1881-1968
AAA.sprealma
Archival Resource Key
0.6 Linear feet
The papers of San Francisco art patron and philanthropist Alma de Bretteville Spreckels measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1978. The collection focuses on Spreckels's founding of and service to the California Palace of the Legion of Honor and the Maryhill Museum of Fine Arts through correspondence, financial and legal records, meeting minutes, photographs, printed material, and registrarial records. Of note are Queen Marie of Romania's handwritten descriptions describing the provenance of her mementos and artifacts donated to the Maryhill Museum of Fine Arts.
Biographical / Historical
Alma de Bretteville Spreckels (1881-1968) was an art patron and socialite from San Francisco, California. Her early childhood was marked by near poverty but her fascination with art led her to studying at the Mark Hopkins Institute of Art (San Francisco Art Institute). Alma worked as an artist model for artists such as Robert Aitken, and she was purportedly the inspiration for Aitken's Dewey Monument in San Francisco.
Alma married the heir of a sugar fortune, Adolph B. Spreckels, with whom she had two children. Following Adolph's death in 1924, Spreckels focused her energies on art patronage and philanthropy, including the founding and sourcing of collections for the Palace of the Legion of Honor and the Maryhill Museum of Art.
Scope and Contents
The papers of San Francisco art patron and philanthropist Alma de Bretteville Spreckels measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1978. The collection focuses on Spreckels's founding of and service to the California Palace of the Legion of Honor and the Maryhill Museum of Fine Arts through correspondence, financial and legal records, meeting minutes, photographs, printed material, and registrarial records. Of note are Queen Marie of Romania's handwritten descriptions describing the provenance of her mementos and artifacts donated to the Maryhill Museum of Fine Arts.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by Mrs. Dorothy Munn, daughter of Alma de Bretteville Spreckles, in 1980.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection is available on 35mm reels 1732-1733 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Decorative arts -- Romania; Art patrons -- California -- San Francisco; Philanthropists -- California -- San Francisco; California Palace of the Legion of Honor; Maryhill Museum of Art
- Alma de Bretteville Spreckels Papers, 1920-1978; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  Spreckels's professional correspondence include letters from Clifford Dolph, Loie Fuller, Walter Heil, Thomas Carr Howe, Malvina Hoffman, Harry Noyes Pratt, Lloyd LaPage Rollins, and Queen Marie of Romania. Financial and legal records contain price lists, insurance valuations, and agreements for Spreckels's donations and loans to museums and other institutions. Also found are records focusing on the formation and running of the California Palace of the Legion of Honor and the Maryhill Museum of Art. Included are meeting minutes and registrarial records which include lists of works of art, valuation records, and donation records. Photographs are of Queen Marie of Romania, her artifacts, and two photos of busts by Malvina Hoffman. Provenance records consist of handwritten and typescripts of Queen Marie's recollections and descriptions of each artifact donated.
  - Correspondence, 1920-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, circa 1920s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Financial Records, 1937-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Legal Records, 1920-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meeting Minutes, California Palace of the Legion of Honor, 1935-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes, Maryhill Museum of the Fine Arts, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1928-circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Printed Material, 1937-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Provenance, Queen Marie of Romania Artifacts, circa 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Registrarial Records, California Palace of the Legion of Honor, 1926-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Registrarial Records, Maryhill Museum of the Fine Arts, 1948-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)